all right greetings thanks for joining
all it's March 29th 2023 we're in cohort
II
in our first discussion on chapter 10.
so
let's head over to chapter 10.
and um
begin with any
comments
really about anything within the active
area
several were voiced before we beat God
so perhaps Terry
feel free to begin with um what you
wanted to point towards and let's just
see where that goes thank you
uh
in in essence my my question is about
the concept of a
[Music]
um
a system of volitional Consciousness
behind that sits behind the uh nodal
active inference model and creating
[Music]
um
uh I suppose uh
making decisions about about the
Strategic direction of the organism and
um I I find just repeatedly within this
chapter there seems to be this reference
to you you know a a conscious entity
behind the algorithm and my sense from
to trying to understand this material is
that it's almost like um
in meditation where you know the the the
the the the
experiences the experience that that
that almost there is no I behind the
experience and that
um
it just jars with me when we're
presented with a
almost complete uh active inference
model or that that where where our our
actions in the world are actually
experiments to gain information about
the external state to
um up up ultimately update the model and
what Consciousness is as you said at the
start is is a difficult concept but
um it seems strange to me within the
context of this model that we refer back
to some sort of uh underpinning
strategic conscious
experiential driver of action when that
seems out with this model
thank you
are unnecessary for this model
um
Michael Raleigh want to give any
first thoughts on this
yeah Ollie go for it
yeah uh well
actually I don't think uh they
necessarily uh somehow
uh I mean the active inference framework
doesn't require any
conscious entity in the sense of our
anthropic sense of this word
Consciousness because
what FTP actually tries to model is a
kind of uh quote-unquote as if
epistemology
still by uh as if epistemology it
doesn't mean that everything that uh can
can be modeled with fpp formulation uh
necessarily
um has
anthropic uh this sense of anthropic
Consciousness but
it's a kind of a kind of uh
self-referential way of talking about uh
the perspective of being modeled so I'm
sure you've encountered this word
self-evidencing throughout this book
which refers to the same concept of as
if epistemology so
it's or
um one of I'm sure Daniel's favorite
figures
um in the book figure yeah 9.1 also
captures this sense of uh perspectival
uh view view of
uh kind of
the nature of this modeling is not that
we have this sense of uh omniscience
that that can be applied uh to the
environment or that can be uh
reasoned through uh with uh I mean
reason through
um
and uh that can also be
applied to our sensorium or perceptorium
but it's like we have this uh model
inside a kind of
apparatus that can see Its Behavior as
if uh following through a kind of
trajectory in the probability density of
space so by volition
uh that you're referring to
it's my understanding that
it's also another term that they've also
used that's related to this
self-evidencing is uh they is the object
or the agent tries to infer its
environment
uh through a kind of uh what was this
term in it was
um something like indirect pers no it
wasn't
um
Daniel can you help me find the term for
uh the indirect perception of the
specific term that's used in the
literature to refer to indirect
perception
uh sorry just a second I don't exactly
remember
okay I'll find it and I'll get back to
you in just one second
okay and I mean I I I I I stop me if I'm
going down some unnecessary Rabbit Hole
um uh
but it's almost as if uh this
um
system
active inference represents a model by
which one could uh create a
psychological zombie
um in in that you know by active
inference without any
um
yeah
extensive internal self one could behave
in the world uh by um you know
minimizing
um
uh variational free energy
in the way that we behave in the world
and
um
Daniel then it seemed to him one of his
books sort of talk about that
um uh the RR you know that we have
active won't rather than active
um uh that that than rather than free
will you know and
um I I suppose the the implication of
that is that we um
that that our conscious reality is is
like a a story We Tell ourselves almost
uh shortly after the event
and yet in this
book there is this reference to uh
uh a conscious will within the within
the framework or is certainly within
that last chapter uh chapter
um uh five that we're isn't it chapter
five we're on today
so I I don't I I I I I mean I don't have
this worked out of my head but um I'm
just interested it's entirely possible
that um one could say active inference
isn't about what it it doesn't speak to
Consciousness Consciousness is another
thing active influence just off uh gives
another is a potential model that uh
drives
um decision making within the organism
almost
and that's okay
um but I'm just in I I'm just interested
in other people's thoughts on this
it's it's it's great
topics so just a few notes
um
broadly
there are perspectives on Consciousness
well first I'll just note Consciousness
appears to be only used once in the book
so while it is true that um it's an area
of interest and was the live stream with
uh vanja Visa
this morning I mean and the authors all
explore elsewhere but
any interpretation of consciousness
I I don't even think it's within the
it's not a pillar of the framework it's
something that is like inferred towards
so I think that will always leave a
fundamental
um uncertainty in pluralism
and then we can think about at least a
gradient of um accounts of Consciousness
in some accounts
Consciousness is um
after the fact
in some way that it could still be
anticipatory
from a predictive processing sense but
it does not have a causal power it's
it's a narrative told
to um let's say minimize variational
free energy to make sense of memories
and so that kind of narrative
expositional self as epiphenomena and
experience without causal impact
and then that is of course contrasted
with causal accounts of consciousness
and that's where whether you come from
some philosophical tradition or certain
folks psychological Traditions
um which both can arise during
scientific writing as well
things like emotions or awareness
or even attention
are actually described as causally
Upstream of other phenomena
and that
puts one of course squarely in the kind
of Cartesian dualism
area of philosophy like how does
something that is not physical
influence something that is physical
um so
the the the the dominant
mode to me on that question
is Consciousness is something we can
model about and around with active
inference but no perspective on
Consciousness seems fundamental to using
statistics in this way
and so I expect and already find
confirmatory evidence that some people
take a more Epi phenomenal approach to
Consciousness and some people taking a
more causal approach for example
treating it like a hidden latent factor
that does have a causal impact in a
causal Bayesian sense
and then also just recognizing yeah we
don't know exactly what it is
that's how we do active modeling we
propose latent clauses
and those become our generative model
so in some ways there may be more
similarities between these two
than their hyperbolic forms suggest
and in either case I feel like it's a
Continuum that's accommodated
methodologically
by what Ali referred to as the as if
epistemology
and that I think connects to Daniel
dennett's intentional stance like I'm
going to play this chess computer like
it's trying to beat me if it's not if
it's to try then I then I want to win
so if it wants me to win two then that's
going to be great
but I'm gonna hedge my bets and play
like it's trying to win
and I think that kind of um intentional
stance
is not just warranted it's actually
supported
by these methodological tools
Terry or Michael
well in some ways and we're getting way
off topic and then I will be quiet oh no
this is we're technically in chapter 10.
so we're we're totally on just recap and
meme status
oh okay but we but it's like but you
would say that wouldn't you you know I I
I if Consciousness isn't after the fact
um uh Story We Tell ourselves
um you know it it's at the model
if the world is probably more likely
that one finds oneself in front of a
computer play playing chess uh because
of the you know all of the previous
events that have occurred during your
your life and that you are now playing
chess so the story you tell yourself is
that I'm going to play to win but
actually that it wasn't the it wasn't
the conscious decision that got you
there if Consciousness is and after the
fact
uh
uh you know hallucination or or story
that we that we create to
um
justify the things that are happening in
the external in the on the One external
State you know because the computer is
in the unknown external State it's it's
a it's something that we have internally
created
um uh as our model based on the
information we're getting across our
Markov blanket am I getting too mad I'll
give a short note and then Ali so
um one answer from a biological
perspective is especially over
evolutionary time but also within a
generation
you will only repeatedly observe
things that are
fighting to live and persisting amidst
challenging and adversarial settings so
if we just say oh well just the person
in front of the computer what would be
subconsciously leading them to want to
win but if we say we're in a chess
tournament series
and only people who have won previous
chess tournaments
defined by winning in this arbitrary way
only they are persisting in this
tournament
well then
over time
you will come to find that those agents
are acting as if they want to win at
chess
now then there's the debate well what if
they're just acting like they want to
win at chess but they don't really want
to win they're they're chess zombies
they're just acting like it and then
that's the pluralism
some people look at that chess
tournament sequence and they go yeah I
actually have like reasons to think that
people don't have experience or
intentions or that Consciousness is just
a narrative told after the fact and so
they're just acting like they want to
win
and the other person tells us extremely
intimate causal story
about how the the motivation of the
person
drives their action selection
but in the end they're unified by this
as if epistemology which is to say the
intentional stance
Ali
uh yeah also this uh kind of as if
epistemology
comes from at least partially comes from
uh kantian transcendental idealism so
for uh Concepts do not
apply to reality in the form in which we
can only think them but
um
it is also urgently required for any
theoretical practice to think and
investigate
objects uh with the help of the concepts
as if they were given or determined
um in a specific way so this kind of as
if epistemology
um
is it you see uh Concepts have to
um acknowledge that a reality is
presuppose independently of the choice
of uh its semantics or its meanings on
the other hand in their self-reference
and self similarity uh they work with
this heuristic of as if
so that uh it can be constructed in this
way as if reality and concept would
actually coincide with each other but
some recent philosophers such as Karen
broad attempts to overcome this kind of
as if epistemology uh for example in her
agent of realism agential realism and by
means of construction of interactive
discursive in which both epistemology
and and ontology can be seen as the very
same thing and we wouldn't be required
to
draw a boundary between the perception
on the one hand and the thing that we're
trying to percept or model on the other
hand so through this uh intraction not
interaction but interaction uh or
constructive interaction uh
they constitute each other so as they
give rise to their very existence and uh
also I think in some View
FTP is perfectly compatible with this
more
loose sense of onto epistemology because
one of the requirements of the fpp is if
things exist
how they should behave right so it's
somehow presupposes this kind of
interactive
discourse
by
basically eliminating the boundary
between the thing that we're trying to
model and
um I mean the the model the model or the
map so that's basically uh the argument
behind that map territory fallacy
fallacy uh so uh yeah this is a bit uh
more complicated uh in in this sense
that uh if we want to get to the bottom
of this kind of epistemology uh we will
hit a dead end if we just
um
if we just uh go through this more
traditional epistemology of uh of
Western epistemology of uh
distinguishing between the thing that
what we're trying to perceive and the
perception itself uh but as I said fep
somehow tries to overcome this problem
in the first place
hmm
that's that's beautifully
um uh described
um
and nicely closed down
and that the thing that I was thinking
initially was
um the assumption that in the external
State there's actually AHS competition
happening
um is assuming almost this uh car you
know uh that that that are
um internal state representation is an
accurate or a true likeness of what the
external status which I think Holly was
kind of saying but um I I my my sense is
that it clearly can't be because all of
our
um all of our all of our qualia are
um uh
Endeavors that the the the the the the
the the central nervous system uh makes
to interpret
um signals that are generated without
the qualia that we apply to them
yeah you know these are these are great
one sure thought then Michael
um yeah the internal state
does not in the model does not have to
have the same structure as the external
state so like often we'll talk about
well the external state in the model
could be a continuous temperature and
the internal State could just be maybe
too hot just right or too cold so they
can have different structure
and that reflects that they don't even
have to be of the same type even within
the model let alone the territory
however
by the cybernetic principles like good
regulator theorem
again eventually you can always just
create an edge case
where the agent has no
um mapping between their internal
cognitive Dynamics and the external
regularities like it's just playing the
game randomly with respect to the
environmental variability
and in a research or an education
setting that may be pedagogical but when
we're talking about real measurements
that we made even of like the the pen on
my desk
it is resisting dissipation over some
spatial temporal time scale
and that is actually
the surprising
implication of if things exist
how they should behave
is like well I am repeatedly measuring
this pen
so now what can I say about that and it
turns out you can actually say a lot
if you bake into your understanding that
you are observing something repeatedly
existing
and that's exactly what we see in figure
9.1
and so we we have a a Unity of the
scenario
in our model
via articulating
the partitions on a base graph
so that means they're still totally up
in the air map and territory and all of
that
but within our model
we're we're approaching that in a way
that sets the stage for people to then
take further perspectives about deeper
questions
Michael
yeah I I think that these questions may
be uh somehow relate to this Tale of Two
density papers
um great you mentioned last time so and
I my understanding of this paper is that
they
um try to argue that there's no
representation
in the mind but the mind is a controlled
system and then they talk about two
different distributions that I so so uh
so so one distribution is the
recognition distribution and the other
one is the generative system if I
understood correctly but I didn't really
understand how
this distribution how this this
distribution comes into being through
the
um generative system so that equal one
with an enacted so the recognition
system is the an embodied system and the
generative system is the enacted system
and my understanding is that this is all
that there is so for instance they say
here the
on page 235 the generative model
manifests as a control system that uses
exploitable structural similarities
encoded in the internal states of the
organism
so instead of having representations
they talk about
controlled States
and to understand this correct so how
can that be um
a distribution
or
um
I I didn't really
I didn't really unders understand where
these two distributions are great
all great questions so I'll try to
address some so
um this question of exploitable
similarity
is very much like the good regulator
theorem in cybernetics
so it doesn't mean that the temperature
in the room let's just say that it's
physiologically relevant
so there have to be some sensors and
some processing apparatus and also
action apparatus but at the very least
just for cognition a sensory and
processing apparatus
that is able to like measure
temperature
it can be a proxy of it doesn't need to
be a strict isomorphism they say it's
weaker than a strict isomorphism
but it actually has to have some sort of
causal relevance now if you're like well
I'm in a simulation where the
temperature is fluctuating but it has no
survival value then it's like okay
that's like saying you know cosmic rays
are going through us they don't have
survival value and so
they're not part of the cognitive model
in this setting
um but
um this points to this idea that there
is information in the sensory apparatus
about action it's actionable
intelligence with respect to persistence
why persistence well we could say in
pursuit of reward but then we would need
to ask how systems persist
why persistence because we're at least
repeatedly measuring the system
so again with the as if epistemology
it's as if in order to persist
amidst dissipative and adversarial
settings
it's as if
there's an exploitable information
content in the perceptual
umvelt
that enables that kind of thing
to persist
that's like the tautology that also goes
beyond a tautology now to the specifics
of the tale of two densities
um this also might have been the first
dot zero in in six I'm I'm not sure
in Bayesian statistical analysis
models can be run in two different
directions
this could be like a hyper prior and and
um here's the hyper priorities on the
right
and the data are on the left
so it's like you can specify the hyper
prior or the hidden State distribution
and you can emit pseudo data that's
called generative
or you can have data and then
parameterize hidden States
that's the recognition model so this
could be the actual measurements of
children's height in the classroom
here's our generative statistical model
gaussian family mean and variance
so given a mean and a variance estimator
two numbers
metaphysical statistical we can generate
infinite class size of synthetic height
data or from one height observation or
more
we can update our generative model of
the world okay
then
more broadly we're interested in this
relationship between the world and the
agent agent in the niche
so perception and how that updates the
agent's learning and uh and perception
and then how the agent acts on the world
and what they argue in this paper
is that the recognition model in a
Bayesian statistical setting so going
from measurements which might be noisy
and the the height in centimeters isn't
like the real height of the person the
number on the scale isn't the weight the
number on thermometer is not the
temperature like it's data this is why
the empirical perspective on behavioral
modeling is so essential because when we
go on this Bayesian side it's really
easy to talk about how data are
recognized and update hyper parameters
and then hyper parameters can be in the
business of continually generating
unfolding predictions
we have a noisy camera with a blind spot
we're updating our generative model of
vision
and then we're going to be in this case
just creating more synthetic Vision data
in an activism and all of the associated
E's embodiment Etc et cetera et cetera
et cetera
they are focused on
the materiality
of the engagement of the agent with the
world
in this paper Tale of Two densities
they draw these two together
to argue
in the context of
what we'll just point to in figure 4.3
with the a matrix
here two
there's a generative
production
of synthetic observations you could use
it that way
that's the generative direction of a or
you could use a in its recognition
capacity to update hidden States from
observations
so even without getting into the
generativity of action
which is what Indian activists setting
what they're most interested in
is the actual causal consequences of
action
just within a figure
um
4.3
hidden State inference
we can think about a tale of two
densities
and about how Bayesian statistics helps
reconcile this Tale of Two densities
because the same generative model which
is just what we call whatever base graph
you construct the generative model
can be used
equally flexibly to do inference about
any part of it like maybe
um you know the hidden States but you're
trying to determine the prior
so these graphs are agnostic as to what
you know and what you want to infer
now it turns out that for real settings
that we find in the behavioral lab and
out in the fields
we get observations
we don't have access to Hidden States
but we want to infer them
we don't even think A or B matrices or D
matrices exist in the world we purely
want to infer them as statistical
parameters
and then we want to know about action
and in some settings
we have the
um organism's trace of actions
and we're trying to infer their
cognitive parameters
that's the figure 9.1 setting
we saw their actions
it was data for us
and we're looking to parameterize a
cognitive model for them
another setting is we don't know what
action will be taken because we're the
ones taking it
and that is like a prospective
application of these types of models
to take ongoing streams of observations
and then perform action selection in the
moment
but these Frameworks are enormously
General
with whether they're used for online or
offline inference
and like what you actually have access
to measuring and how
so little long but the tailor two
densities
is about how the Bayesian epistemology
and structuring of the relationship
between observations and inferences
about observations
maps in the inactivist setting
to some aspects of how we think about
perception cognition and action in the
niche
and their paper
positions that
within the debates around representation
because representation are although
there's different perspectives Etc
postulated to be like the on agent
aspects
that have semantics about the world
yeah and they say the agent just
controls
the world through their own actions
that's my understanding
yeah
yeah so then then the two densities are
on the incoming side and in the out
outcoming side
okay that's the idea
the density is not the the constitution
of the states of the internal States but
the observable actions
we may be stretching the tale of two
densities making more of a um
an
um a set of novels around densities
because it's just ultimately a cultural
reference
the the technical point
is that these variables are statistical
distributions and hence they are
densities their statistical densities
over some support
so
the two densities that we might be
interested in or amongst two of the ones
that we're interested in making a
unified account of
are the perceptual density
which is about how data map on to Hidden
States
like given retinal data
is that a car
that's a recognition model
and then there's kind of like
two kinds of generative densities you
could run that car recognition model
backwards
say given the label of a car
generate me cars stable diffusion
generative AI
but then there's also this action as a
generative
step
that brings in the actionable
and cybernetic
um constraints
which is why they focus on
um
the exploitable
similarity
but in general Bayesian models you can
do this kind of observable hidden State
inference about anything
the organism Bayesian brain or if we
choose to use Bayesian statistics
it's going to be doing something like
that
the world has a real temperature which
is like molecules moving at different
speeds
perception occurs through sensors
which transform whatever it is the
molecules are doing into something
totally totally different
can I just uh make a little uh point
about that that um that I I remember
watching you know Richard Feynman
just a short video where he was
describing temperature is actually
infrared radiation which is part of the
electromagnetic spectrum so on one part
of that Spectrum we see light and on the
other we experience temperature so
temperatures actually a proxy for
um something else that you know
what we the the mechanism that we have
to perceive temperature is then a proxy
for the amount of energy within that for
example room so it it's not our response
to the infrared information
is is a response that's not based on
infra necessarily that infrared is going
to damage us it's that there's too much
energy in this room and the tool that I
have uh to assess that energy in the
room is actually
monitoring the infrared uh radiation
which I can't see but I can feel any
comment on that
yeah like by analogy
um how about tasting different foods and
there might be a toxin like we can't
directly tell that something is going to
be contaminated but over time successful
entities in an unchanging niche
now that's not every case but just with
that simple case at first
successful entities
in an unchanging Niche will come to
exploit similarities
which is to say Mutual informations
between the recognition model and the
actionability
and so they don't need to be directly
measuring or even internally
representing this is going to make me
sick or this is the wavelength of light
um all any and all
informative cues
of sensors
are going to be
aligned towards adaptive action
that's the synthesis of signal
processing and control theory in active
inference
and it turns out that by by taking a
first principled approach
to the synthesis of those two fields
again just coarsely
we have new insights on the question of
representation
in cognitive science
[Music]
um
yes
but taste is a very interesting
phenomenon and that we have sweet salts
are bitter and yet there are I think
there are trillions of different tastes
that we can that we can uh that we can
actually uh create or
um
are I think smell is probably associated
with taste as well so you know from a
limited amount of sensory information we
can create a vast array of
um
experience
yeah I mean with the um the Jolly
Ranchers I don't know just a candy had
in childhood like they literally taste
the same if you don't see the color but
if you do see the color
even if you try to forget they will
taste different so yeah so different
um that's like referred to as Sensor
Fusion
difference sensors can come together in
the generative model
and it really speaks to the prediction
yeah well it really speaks to what are
our what are our prayers you know
another kind of mind bender on this is
like the visual example there's so much
abundant
um on-ramps to predictive processing
like we don't notice our blind spot we
don't have any blur when we do the
isocate several times per second because
of sensory attenuation you know color
vision and Precision in the periphery
okay I'm on board with a generative
model of vision I'm I've kind of
dispelled this sort of incoming
information camera processing model of
vision I really believe in the visual
generative model getting updated and
it's like but taste
it's like
Yeah by extension what does that really
mean that we're generating our taste
experience well then why wouldn't I just
generate tastes that tastes amazing like
well why what why wouldn't your
generative model of vision just generate
what you like to see
and that's where the real organismal
constraints and where appeals to our
development ecology and evolution do
come into play so again contrived
gedenken can be proposed
absent these super obvious constraints
for real systems
however in the context of empirical
behavioral modeling
it's usually sufficient to say the prior
Distribution on this
or the trade-off between these two
different drives
is inherited from history and
development or even from
intergenerational processes
but but but isn't is it that we generate
a good taste going to a baker where we
like to go
and doing and going towards those areas
where we get those kinds of rewards that
we prefer
I don't know why
yes okay okay here we were okay chapter
seven
we were engaged in a policy vacillation
we were not sure if we were wanting to
get bread or if we want to go to Barber
so now
um
the question of the taste yes if we
expect and prefer a given taste like
sweet and I think this
holds true for sugar but it can hold
true for other things too
then
in the free energy evaluation of
different policies with expected free
energy
expecting observations that align with
your preferences
will be associated with pragmatic value
so that is how preference for sweeter
tastes
puts its thumb on the scale of policy
selection
biases policy selection towards
tasting sugar as a pragmatic reward
but that happens amidst
a relationship with epistemic value as
well
so it's like
um epistemic value could be pursued
like we need to find out how to get to
the baker
I mean there's there's many ways to go
but yes you would parameterize a
generative model
with a preference
let's think about this this case with
sugar in the baker in those two settings
that we described so in one case
we're in figure 9.1
and we're we're observing people's
behavior
so we have their credit card history
whoops
and we're observing who
is going to the baker or what they're
ordering
or what they're clicking on online
and now we're going to do inference on a
generative model for them it's the as if
generative model
and it's like wow this person
has a very strong C Vector very strong
preference Vector for sugar
like given Alternatives they're always
going for the sweeter one
and this person has a neutral preference
for sugar and this person actually like
like moves away from sugar
as represented by our parameterization
of the C vector
so that's one setting we have data on a
bunch of different entities
on what they chose in different sugar
concentrations
and then the other setting would be now
step into the trajectory of one of those
cognitive models
and now ask what your next action should
be
and that's the as if a gentle
or intentional stance
so this is the behavioral scientists
view from the outside
and then that is going to be flexible
with allowing us also to take views as
if from the inside
and just because we can take an as if
View From the Inside
doesn't mean that that's the territory
that's literally the map territory
fallacy
but it means that within the limits of
our
cognitive model
we do have that opportunity
um
uh what one of the things that strikes
me is you talk about this is is the
um
one of the interviews Carl friston has
done online he talks about you know our
actions during during the day that you
know we get up and we
um have our breakfast and then we
um you know we we go to the bus and we
get go to work and we do our work but we
I you know and actually most of our life
is
um little routines we we think that we
have these independent lives where we
are constantly making uh decisions about
what what you know what what what do I
want to eat today what where will I go
but actually the person who ends up
going to the baker will find that on
their walk to the bus stop they pass the
bakery and they get a trigger from the
smell of the bakery to do the thing that
you know to predict that it's it's it's
just it's interesting that we don't
exist
but as these completely independent no
matter where you live no matter who you
are there are so many aspects of your
life that are just so so repeatable that
we actually live within a very
constricted box apart from odd times
when we step outside that box I I I I
don't know if that's relevant to what to
that picture but oh it's awesome I mean
very very interesting to point to the
state of exception in live stream 10
with um Mao and ramstead at all who are
the other authors Mao Axel Carl and
Maxwell
um they talk about like strong and weak
Scripts a strong script in a social
setting would be like if we were
literally reading from a screenplay
or if we were doing some sort of Highly
ritualized Behavior
whereas the weaker script concept refers
to like Norms normativity expectations
X kind of person should act like this
I'm X kind of person
I would be unsurprised by doing X up
what do you know I'm doing X
and that kind of progressive identity
capture
and development of
understanding what kind of thing one is
and then
what are the two ways you can reduce
your discrepancy you can change you can
learn change what you think that kind of
thing is and you can act
so undergrad should act this way you
know I expect here's the distribution of
undergrads if one's um
understanding of what an undergrad was
was totally flat with respect to
everything there's nothing that
characterizes
an undergrad versus anything else just
from one person's perspective well then
that aspect of their identity wouldn't
shape their policy selection
whereas if someone says well as a x
I should be doing why
that can be approached from a purely
statistical deflationary perspective
like I just expect myself to be doing
this
like
or it can go even beyond that too
so those are these are all very relevant
and learning about the fundamentals of
this kind of statistical modeling
help us
I hope I prefer also that it helps us
actually respect the complexity and the
richness of these phenomena
which just simply cannot be expressed in
words or math
which is why we talk about the map
yeah one of my wonderings about all this
because I do find the maths and the uh
the the pictures and the diagrams all
very difficult to to to grasp
um
in some way it is there a potential that
if we really understood the model we
could start uh uh use that as a system
to inform
our understanding of
individual behaviors
I mean I'm a pain doctor so I um my my
my
um my interest and all this is this this
this this truth that we can alter our
you know if you are in pain if you have
back pain you can alter your prediction
about your back pain and actually alter
your back pain and I'm just wondering if
this kind of modeling could in some way
give us a tool to help us to
support other humans in understanding
their ability that they can update their
prayers you know
yeah it's a great
Vision I think the closest that we've
explored that is
um with the help of Ian tenants
who has a interception
um focus and this Therapeutic Alliance
concept where where a lot of these kind
of avenues and like it's not as simple
as just wish it away
any more than the generative model of
vision would be like I want to see you
know a unicorn in front of me
so how do we reconcile
that agential realism that Ali mentioned
earlier like
this active co-construction and
negotiation
and sense making from our sensorium
and the ways that our narratives and the
scripts and the expectations shape our
inference and action
um
and
choose to have a preference
and to act to push things in a certain
way
yeah
absolutely
yeah but but but
I I suppose what what I'm kind of
thinking is could you have a like a a ma
you know a a Sam Altman created model
where you run the model and that can
inform how that can inform
the uh
understanding of an individuals how they
got there and potentially offer some
insights into what to do about it you
know that that could this speak to a
model that could be run where we could
kind of do the experiment and then that
supports an individual on actually going
on the course of action
to change their experience
that that's that's kind of where I what
what what really blows my mind about
this and that in the current world that
it has only come into existence in the
past month or so this actually seems
almost plausible
because because of the the similar
layered nodal systems that the likes of
chati PT are using to protect language
yes it's a great it's not active you
know it's not active you could model it
around a notion of active inference and
that you know the the training of the
system
there's there's so many Avenues to
explore there let's in our discussion
next week let's look at
um that again but absolutely with
respect to
figure 9.1s about us
the data exists
the means motive opportunity
anyone who wants to
can do things
and that's a big question
so for next week
thank you though I'll stop recording so